Finding Aid for Edward Bruce Williamson papers, 1891-1950
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edward Bruce Williamson papers
1891-1950
1899-1933
Williamson, Edward Bruce, 1878-1933.
0799 Aa 2
Edward Bruce Williamson was a noted entomologist and botanist in the early part of the 20th century. He spent most of his career as an amateur, but active and well-respected, scholar of odonata (dragon and damselflies) and served as the curator of odonata for the University of Michigan Museum of Zoology from 1916 to his retirement in 1933. He also owned and maintained the Longfield Iris Farm in Bluffton, Indiana where he propagated award-winning irises. The collection includes correspondence, drawing, field notes and reports from his collecting trips, and photographs.
7 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was donated to the library in April of 2007 by the University of Michigan Museum of Zoology (donor no. 837 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Edward Bruce Williamson was born into a banking family in Bluffton, Indiana. Williamson joined the family business as a clerk, and took over as president of the Wells County Bank in 1918. Though he retained banking as his profession, his true interest was not finance, but biology. He had a profound interest in entomology, and in particular odonata, the order of insects encompassing dragon and damselflies. He went on frequent odonata collecting trips, often accompanied by his cousin and fellow dragonfly enthusiast, Jess Williamson. These trips took him as far Venezuela and Trinidad, though much of his research focused on the dragonflies of Indiana and the American Midwest.
Though Williamson was never a professional scholar, he was considered one of the foremost odonata experts in the world by his colleagues. He was particularly interested in taxonomic entomology and identified a number of new dragonfly species throughout his career. He donated many of the specimens he collected to museums around the country, and was regularly asked to identify species collected by other museums, universities, and scholars. His many correspondents include odonata experts as well as representatives of Chicago's Field Museum, the Smithsonian, and the British Museum. He was a member of the Entomological Society of America, as well as the Indiana, Michigan, and Ohio Academies of Science. He was appointed president of the Indiana Academy of Science in 1918, and was the first man to hold that post for two successive years.
In December, 1916, the University of Michigan Board of Regents, at the recommendation of Alexander Ruthven, appointed E.B. Williamson to the post of curator of odonata at the University of Michigan Museum of Zoology. During his tenure as curator Williamson facilitated the growth and development of an impressive collection of odonata which he made available for research and exhibition. He remained in the post until 1933 when he retired to dedicate his time to his iris farm in Bluffton.
Though the bulk of this collection focuses on Williamson the entomologist he was also a respected botanist and iris breeder. He bred a number of award-winning irises, many of which are still considered premium-breeding stock today. It was this business which supported his family after his bank collapsed at the height of the Great Depression.
The Edward Bruce Williamson collection contains material dating from 1891 and spanning the next forty years until his death in 1933. Most of the collection focuses on Williamson's activities as an entomologist, though also it includes some personal correspondence and photographs. The collection is divided into four series, Correspondence, 1891-1935, Drawings, Miscellaneous, Notes and Paper Drafts, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Williamson, Edward Bruce, 1878-1933.; University of Michigan. Museum of Zoology.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Zoology.; University of Michigan. University Museum.; Dragonflies.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Williamson, Edward Bruce, 1878-1933.; Expeditions and surverys--Colombia.; Expeditions and surveys--Venezuela.; Expeditions and surveys--Southern States.; Colombia--Description and travel.; Venezuela--Description and travel.; Southern States--Description and travel.; Dragonflies.
Genre Terms:
Drawings.; Photographs.
- Correspondence, 1891-1935
  The Correspondence series dates from 1891-1935 and comprises the bulk of the collection. The first files in the general correspondence contain various letters from individuals and organizations that were not regular correspondents of Williamson's. The rest, and majority, of the correspondence is organized by correspondent. These files contain letters from the foremost odonata experts working contemporaneously with Williamson, as well as early luminaries in the field of museum studies working at museums as diverse as Chicago's Field Museum, the British Museum, the American Museum of Natural History, and Pittsburgh's Carnegie Museum. While the majority of this correspondence relates to the identification and classification of dragonfly specimens, the collection also contains letters from Alexander Ruthven and Frederick Gaige relating to the U of M Museum of Zoology, and epistolary exchanges with friends and colleagues that give insight into Williamson's personality beyond his entomological interests.
  - General
    - A-C, 1899-1933 (Box 1)
    - D-F, 1902-1932 (Box 1)
    - G-J, 1898-1933 (Box 1)
    - K-L, 1911-1933 (Box 1)
    - M, 1900-1932 (Box 1)
    - N-Q, 1900-1932 (Box 1)
    - R, 1899-1933 (Box 1)
    - S, 1900-1932 (Box 1)
    - T-V, 1903-1932 (Box 1)
    - W, 1899-1932 (Box 1)
    - Y-Z, 1902-1931 (Box 1)
  - Adams, C.C., 1899-1923 (Box 1)
  - Allen, G.M., 1902 (Box 1)
  - Aldrich, J.M., 1916-1933 (Box 1)
  - Alexander, C.P., 1911-1932 (Box 1)
  - Atkinson, D.A., 1899-1932; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Baker, C.T., 1905-1920 (Box 1)
  - Baker, H.B., 1919-1926 (Box 1)
  - Banks, N., 1901-1933 (Box 1)
  - Banta, A.M., 1901-1914 (Box 1)
  - Bartenef, A.N., 1909-1931 (Box 1)
  - Bassett, C.C., 1900-1901 (Box 1)
  - Becker, H.R., 1909-1930 (Box 1)
  - Belmontes,G., 1931-1932 (Box 1)
  - Benjamin, M., 1904-1915 (Box 1)
  - Bennett, L.F., 1917 (Box 1)
  - Bentivoglio, Tito, 1908 (Box 1)
  - Billinghurst, F.M., 1905 (Box 1)
  - Bird, R.D., 1929-1933 (Box 1)
  - Blatchley, W.S., 1897-1927 (Box 2)
  - Bonis, F., 1904-1906 (Box 2)
  - Borror, D.J., 1930-1933 (Box 2)
  - Bradley, J.C., 1909-1924 (Box 2)
  - Brauer, 1903 (Box 2)
  - Bridwell, L.H., 1930-1932 (Box 2)
  - Brimley, C.S., 1903-1925 (Box 2)
  - Broadway, W.E., 1913-1918 (Box 2)
  - Brown. W.H., 1899-1904 (Box 2)
  - Brunetti, E., 1905 (Box 2)
  - Bueno, J.R. dela Torre, 1902-1906 (Box 2)
  - Busch, A., 1910-1913 (Box 2)
  - Butler, A.W., 1907-1923 (Box 2)
  - Byers, C. F., 1925-1932 (Box 2)
  - Calvert, P.P., 1898-1930; 12 folders (Box 2)
  - Calvert, P.P., 1931-1933 (Box 3)
  - Calvert, P.P., undated (Box 3)
  - Campion, H., 1919-1924 (Box 3)
  - Carpenter, G.H., 1901-1904 (Box 3)
  - Clark, H.W., 1900-1917 (Box 3)
  - Cockerell, D.A., 1907-1930 (Box 3)
  - Collins, F., 1907 (Box 3)
  - Combs, A.F., 1915-1931 (Box 3)
  - Cory, C.B., 1912-1920 (Box 3)
  - Coulter, J.M., 1904-1925 (Box 3)
  - Crampton, G.C., 1918 (Box 3)
  - Crampton. H.E., 1911 (Box 3)
  - Currie, R.P. & B.P, 1900-1922; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Carriker, M.A., 1916-1927 (Box 3)
  - Davis, J.J., 1919-1932 (Box 3)
  - Davis, W.T., 1913-1933 (Box 3)
  - Deam, C.C., 1898-1931 (Box 3)
  - Dietz, H.T., 1910-1932 (Box 3)
  - Ditzler, W.H., 1921-1932 (Box 3)
  - Donaldson, S., 1906-1907 (Box 3)
  - Dury, C., 1900-1919 (Box 3)
  - Earnshaw, R.A., 1899-1911 (Box 3)
  - Eigenmann, C.H., 1898-1923 (Box 3)
  - Elrod, M.J., 1901-1906 (Box 3)
  - Enders, H.E., 1916-1923 (Box 3)
  - Engel, H., 1901-1902 (Box 3)
  - Evermann, B.W., 1894-1923 (Box 3)
  - Faxon, W., 1897-1899 (Box 3)
  - Field, H.H., 1903-1919 (Box 3)
  - Fisher, M.L., 1913-1917 (Box 3)
  - Foley, A.L., 1923 (Box 3)
  - Forbes, S.A., 1902-1915 (Box 3)
  - Förster, F., 1899-1927 (Box 3)
  - Förster, R., 1906-1930 (Box 3)
  - Foster, E., 1898-1923 (Box 3)
  - Franz, Elli, 1932 (Box 3)
  - Fraser, F.C., 1922-1954 (Box 3)
  - Fudakowski, J., 1932 (Box 3)
  - Fuller, E.L., 1900-1901 (Box 3)
  - Fyles, T.W., 1903-1904 (Box 3)
  - Gaige, F., 1916-1927; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Gaige, F., 1928-1932 (Box 4)
  - Garman, P., 1915-1927 (Box 4)
  - Geddes, J.M., 1912-1930 (Box 4)
  - Geijskes, D.C., 1930-1931 (Box 4)
  - Germain, Bro., 1913 (Box 4)
  - Gerhard, W.J., 1919-1930 (Box 4)
  - Gloyd, H., 1930-1932 (Box 4)
  - Graf, J.L., 1898-1925 (Box 4)
  - Gregor, D.K., 1907 (Box 4)
  - Grinnell, F., 1900-1906 (Box 4)
  - Grimberg, K., 1903-1904 (Box 4)
  - Hankinson, T.L., 1906-1918 (Box 4)
  - Harris, 1908-1912 (Box 4)
  - Hart, C.A., 1901-1917 (Box 4)
  - Harvey, A.L., 1900 (Box 4)
  - Hay, W.P., 1900-1906 (Box 4)
  - Henshaw, S., 1898-1923 (Box 4)
  - Higgins, M.L., 1922-1924 (Box 4)
  - Hine, J.S., 1898-1931; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Holland, W.J., 1899-1931 (Box 4)
  - Hood, J.D., 1909-1932 (Box 4)
  - Howard, L.O., 1921 (Box 4)
  - Howe, R.H. Jr., 1915-1923 (Box 4)
  - Howe, W.T.H., 1900 (Box 4)
  - Indiana Academy of Science, 1918-1919 (Box 4)
  - Juday, C., 1903-1916 (Box 4)
  - Kahl, H., 1916-1932 (Box 4)
  - Kellerman, W.A., 1898-1905 (Box 4)
  - Kellicott, 1895-1910 (Box 4)
  - Kimmins, D.E., 1930-1933 (Box 4)
  - Kirby, W.F., 1899-1912 (Box 4)
  - Laidlaw, F.F., 1911-1932 (Box 4)
  - Lacroix, J.L., 1924-1932 (Box 4)
  - Leigh, G.F., 1904-1914 (Box 4)
  - Lieftinck, M.A., 1928-1932 (Box 4)
  - Light, S.F., 1909 (Box 4)
  - Link, G.A., 1907 (Box 4)
  - Livermore, E., 1920 (Box 4)
  - Loomis, H., 1904-1907 (Box 4)
  - Lucas, W.J., 1917-1931 (Box 4)
  - Lund, W., 1910-1914 (Box 4)
  - Lutz, F.E., 1914-1930 (Box 4)
  - Kennedy, C., 1900-1915; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Kennedy, C., 1916-1932; 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Kinsey, A., 1920-1933 (Box 5)
  - MacGillivray, A.D., 1917-1921 (Box 5)
  - McDunnough, J., 1922-1933 (Box 5)
  - McLachlan, R & H, 1900-1932 (Box 5)
  - Marshall, G.A.K., 1899-1905 (Box 5)
  - Martin, R., 1898-1921 (Box 5)
  - Medsgar, O.B., 1900-1901 (Box 5)
  - Menger, E., 1919-1922 (Box 5)
  - Meek, S.E., 1903-1908 (Box 5)
  - Miller, N., 1905-1913 (Box 5)
  - Monkhaus, W.J., 1900-1902 (Box 5)
  - Montgomery, B.E., 1923-1933; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Morris, E.L., 1912 (Box 5)
  - Morton, K.J., 1903-1932 (Box 5)
  - Muttkowski. R.A., 1908-1924; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Navas, L., 1930-1935 (Box 5)
  - Needham, J., 1899-1933; 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Oguma, K., 1911-1930 (Box 5)
  - Orton, E., 1896-1898 (Box 5)
  - Osburn, R.C., 1899-1923; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Oslar, E.J., 1913 (Box 5)
  - Parker, J.B., 1899-1906 (Box 5)
  - Parker, J.B., 1907-1932 (Box 6)
  - Pearse, A.S., 1910-1933 (Box 6)
  - Peterson, E., 1906-1920 (Box 6)
  - Porter, A.F., 1912-1932 (Box 6)
  - Rathbun, R., 1900-1916 (Box 6)
  - Ravenel, W. de C., 1902-1920 (Box 6)
  - Rehn, J., 1915-1918 (Box 6)
  - Rhodes, S.N., 1899-1915 (Box 6)
  - Riley, C.F., 1907-1932 (Box 6)
  - Ris, V., 1901-1932; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Ruthven, A., 1908-1932; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Schmidt, E., 1926-1931 (Box 6)
  - Schmidt, R., 1914 (Box 6)
  - De Selys, 1900-1901 (Box 6)
  - Severn, G., 1905-1930 (Box 6)
  - Shafer, J.M., 1900-1904 (Box 6)
  - Sjöstedt, Y., 1908-1931 (Box 6)
  - Skinner, H., 1905-1910 (Box 6)
  - Snow, L.H., 1904-1932 (Box 6)
  - Spieth, H., 1929-1931 (Box 6)
  - Tepper, J.G.O., 1902-1906 (Box 6)
  - Thomas, E., 1931-1932 (Box 6)
  - Tillyard, R.J., 1907-1933; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Todd, W.E.G., 1899-1909 (Box 6)
  - Tough, J., 1899-1929 (Box 6)
  - Townsend, C.H., 1910 (Box 6)
  - Tsao, Y.S., 1907 (Box 6)
  - Tucker, E.S., 1904-1906 (Box 6)
  - Urich, F.W., 1913-1916 (Box 6)
  - Valle, K.J., 1929-1933 (Box 6)
  - Wadsworth, M., 1901-1923 (Box 6)
  - Walker, E.M., 1905-1933; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Weith, R.J., 1898-1902 (Box 6)
  - Wheldon, A.D., 1900-1918 (Box 6)
  - Whitehouse, F.C., 1917-1920 (Box 6)
  - Wilcox, E.M., 1897-1905 (Box 6)
  - Williamson Family, 1891-1928 (Box 6)
  - Wilson, C.B., 1906-1916 (Box 6)
  - Winslow, M.L., 1920-1927 (Box 6)
  - Wurzlow, E.C., 1914-1918 (Box 6)
- Drawings
  The Drawings series contains Williamson's anatomical drawings of odonata. The series includes both Williamson's original drawings and plates made from them for publication purposes. Many of these plates were used in Williamson's book Dragonflies of Indiana.
  - Original Drawings, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Plates (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series contains Williamson's personal and professional papers, as well as clippings relating to "bug hunting". Included in this series are catalogs from the Longfield Iris Farm, materials relating to collecting expeditions, and lists of awards and honors. Also included are lists of species either discovered by or named for Williamson.
  - Awards and Memberships, 1898-1932 (Box 7)
  - Clippings (Box 7)
  - Collecting Expeditions, 1909-1924 (Box 7)
  - Longfield Iris Catalogs, 1929-1950; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - New Species (Box 7)
- Notes and Paper Drafts
  The Notes and Paper Drafts series includes field notes and reports from Williamson's collecting trips as well as drafts and reviews of scientific papers and articles.
  - "Biological Conditions of Round and Shriner Lakes, Whitley County, Indiana" (Box 7)
  - "A Census of Neurocordulias (Dragonflies)" (Box 7)
  - "Common Names for Dragonflies (Odonata)" (Box 7)
  - "Dragonflies Collected in Kentucky, Tennessee, North and South Carolina, and Georgia in 1931" (Box 7)
  - Field Notes
    - 1923 (Box 7)
    - 1930 (Box 7)
    - Undated (Box 7)
  - Filed Reports
    - 1913 (Box 7)
    - 1923 (Box 7)
    - Undated (Box 7)
  - "Five New Mexican Dragonflies (Odonata)", 1923 (Box 7)
  - "A New North American Somatochlora (Odonata-Cordulinae)" (Box 7)
  - "Notes on the Red-Shouldered Hawk in Indiana", 1913 (Box 7)
  - A Review of "A Contribution to the Knowledge of Florida Odonata", 1930 (Box 7)
  - "Some Peculiarities of the Dragonfly Fauna of Trinidad", 1923 (Box 7)
  - Tables of Coryphaeschua Study (Box 7)
  - "Two New Species of Stylurus", 1931 (Box 7)
  - "The Upper Wabash River, Past, Present, and Future" (Box 7)
  - Venezuela Trip (Box 7)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series contains three photo albums as well as a number of loose photographs. The albums contain snapshots and document various collecting trips in and out of the United States. The loose photographs are a mix of snapshots and portraits of E.B. Williamson or photographs of odonata.
  - Album-Collecting Trips to Columbia and Venezuela, 1916-1920 (Box 7)
  - Album-Southern U.S. Collecting Trip, 1931 (Box 7)
  - Album, Undated (Box 7)
  - E.B. Williamson (Box 7)
  - Odonata (Box 7)